I think social media
is on the cusp of the biggest change it's
had in a very, very
long time.
And if people don't make the necessary
steps to look at social media a
certain way,
they're going to get left behind.
We have AI on the horizon.
We have more people than ever creating
content.
And whereas some of us, including myself,
were very early in our niches to get
online and create a personal brand,
people are now realizing now
is the time to do
it.
Where some people relied heavily on paid
ads and some people relied heavily on
other traditional forms of marketing,
now people have started to realize that if
they do not come front
and center of their business
and do exactly what I'm doing
now,
their businesses will get left behind,
and they will not survive.
Now,
I am in the process of building a system
to help everyone that I
work with move to longer form content.
But just before we get into why that is,
we need to go look at a
concept that I've coined that'll help you
understand everything.
There is absolutely no point increasing
the duration of your content or moving
to another platform
if you can't get this very principle
right.
Now, first things first.
Some of you out there have read some of
Alex Hormozi's
stuff, and you're like,
"I've got to niche down.
I've got to niche down." And you don't.
And sometimes nicheing too far can make
this an absolute nightmare.
I want you to imagine
that this pyramid represents the total
amount of followers
that you have. Now, depressingly,
only a very small amount of those people
do or ever will do business with you.
And you guys know
that I'm a big advocate of saying to
people, "Let's improve
conversions by writing better emails.
Let's improve conversions by having a
well-created landing page."
And I would agree
that a lot of the stuff I teach improves
the conversions in there.
However,
we need to look at this bit for a second.
The biggest mistake you can make in
business is looking at these people
that are
never going to buy your stuff
and thinking, "I don't need them."
But you do.
And I call this the fist bump effect.
So I want all of you guys in your personal
brands to be incredibly happy with the
fact that one day you're going to be in
the supermarket,
someone's going to come up
next to you, and they're going to go,
"Oh my God, I've been watching your stuff
online. I absolutely love it.
It's helped me with so much.
But I've never bought anything from you.
I hope that's okay."
And you need to be able to say, "Yeah,
that's absolutely
great," and give them a fist bump. Now,
that can seem ironic.
Why would we want to appease people
that are never going to do business with
us?
Well, imagine right now there
are two different types of people watching
this
video. There are people that
are going to soon be clients
and then those that
aren't.
Even with the YouTube subscriber numbers
that I've got at the moment right
now,
only about 10% have ever done business
with me. 90% haven't.
And that's completely fine. That's okay.
I still live a very good life
and drive an amazing car.
Because right now,
if we think about YouTube for a second,
one of the most
important metrics for success for this
video getting pushed far and wide is
something called average view duration.
What is the average amount of time someone
watches?
So let's say this is going to be an A
person and this is going to be a B person.
We need B people to watch our content,
to enjoy it, to watch it the whole way
through, to share it,
to even tell their friends about it.
And for you to understand this a little
bit better,
I want you to think about this.
When I was a personal trainer and I
was walking the floor,
I would go up to people
that I knew would never make a good
client.
If there was a six foot two, big,
100-kilogram rugby player,
most personal trainers
would look at that person and go, "Well,
he's never going to need a PT." But you're
forgetting the fact that if I go to him,
give him some tips, chat to him,
just present the fact
that I maybe know what I'm on about,
the next time that
person's girlfriend or partner
or auntie or cousin goes,
"I really need a personal
trainer," that big rugby player will go,
"There's a lad called James, and James
seems really switched on.
You should go talk to him." So the first
thing to
consider is those B people,
the people watching this video right now
that are
never, ever, ever going to buy my stuff.
First of all,
if they have an A person in their life who
goes, "Oh, I really need
help with my marketing," they're going to
go check out James Smith.
He's got a business channel.
It's really helpful.
Not to mention,
if nine out of 10 people watch this video
to the end
as freeloading bastards,
that's amazing because YouTube will then
get
a signal going all these B people watch
75% of the video.
They seem to really enjoy it.
They seem to resonate with it.
And once they started, they couldn't stop.
So YouTube is then going to push it to
larger cohorts of people.
So let's say 100 people watch the video.
5% buy, 95% don't. Fine. But
if both parties really enjoy
that video, YouTube
is going to go find a lot of people just
like those people and
put it in front of them. Now, albeit
that 100 could then end up getting shown
to
1,000 people and that bit up there
is probably going to be a lot smaller
because
this audience is going to be a lot colder.
It could even be 1%, 99%.
Without all of these people
that will never buy your stuff,
we cannot get shown to
these people that potentially can.
Now, some of these people
that watch the video will end up going
into that original
OG ecosystem. And over time,
through putting out more content,
more videos, being
there all the time, these people
are going to warm up
and the percentage of them
that do business with you will start to
increase.
Too many people think
that they need to just make content for
people that are going
to do business with them
and I think that's foolish.
They've listened to Alex Hormozi say you
need to niche down.
Alex Hormozi niches the least out of
anyone.
If you sell 2.7 million books
and you have socials with millions
and millions of
followers and you put out 400 pieces of
content a week, that's not niche.
So next time you're ideating a piece of
content, do not over-niche it to a certain
demographic.
Do you understand why people go,
"Hey lesbians, if you're living in
Nottingham and you want to lose weight,"
it's too niche.
The content I put out is to anyone
that wants to make money online using
social
media. Hundreds of thousands
if not millions of people.
I only need a very small cohort of those
to decide to do business with me.
Even in the most pessimistic of numbers,
if you think, okay, only 1% of people that
watch my videos are going to buy my stuff,
keep making content for the other 99%.
Because as you grow that viewership,
that 1% will get larger and larger
and larger.
Okay,
just before we move into the next segment
of the video, if you are someone
that's considered maybe doing business
with me, I've actually created a quiz, and
if you click on that quiz,
the link in the bio,
it will explain to you where the
weaknesses are in your current marketing
and sales setup.
It'll take two minutes.
When you get to the end of this video,
click on that link.
Do that quiz. All right,
let's get to the next part.
So if we think about what I just said down
there, even if we're making a very
generalized video like this one,
which anyone who's using social media
running a
business going into 2026,
you're thinking to yourself,
how can I get clients out of
that? Well, first of all,
we've got the quiz, which
is going to segment people to
whether or not they're right or not.
Some people do that quiz and be like,
"Wow, he's got something for me."
But then we
can utilize things like lead magnets where
I can say, if you want to improve the
conversions that I spoke about
and take that 5% to a 10%,
the second link in the
description is going to be to get the
template for a highly converted landing
page.
That's just an example, although
that will be in the description.
Niching and talking about a bespoke offer
I think should happen in a stage
removed from social media through lead
magnets, email marketing campaigns, et
cetera.
Although we shouldn't optimize for just
going viral, we should probably
have quite generalized videos
that we can get a good amount of people
watching.
Because like I said,
the bottom part of
that pyramid I think are massive for
getting the sales at the top.
If you can go through life helping 95% of
people for
free knowing they're never going to buy
your stuff, that's how you can tap into
pretty much operating a ferocious
business, which sounds counterintuitive,
but I
stand by it.
So the second thing we need to look into
today is the fact that Google
released this study a few years ago saying
that the average person needs to spend
seven hours in front of you.
And I've been mulling it over for a while.
I've spent a bit of time with Daniel
Priestley, who I have huge admiration for.
Out of all the business gurus online,
I'm going to throw it out there, I watch
their content and think to myself,
"This person's chatting shit."
But for some
reason, well, actually no,
for good reason,
when I listen to Daniel Priestley, I'm
like, "Do you know what?
I really agree with that."
Or he will say things, and I
go, "Do you know what? I've thought
that for years,
but I didn't have a word for
it." And he has his 11 seven-four
principle, which
mimics very much what I've been saying in
my live shows about trying to get seven
hours in front of people.
But he says it should be on different
platforms.
I completely agree.
If you think about it right now,
the last few videos that I put
out on my YouTube were incredibly long.
One was about an hour long,
and the one before that was two hours
and 20 minutes
long. The reason being is
if I do a two-hour 20 live stream seminar,
of which
20% of people made it to the very end,
in one video, I've already pretty much
done one third of the amount of raw time
they need to spend in front of me.
And I didn't realize this back in the day
in 2017, 2018.
I used to go live on Facebook for half an
hour every day.
I was like,
"Why are so many people buying from me?"
The question was some of them
had spent hours in front of me watching me
do my lives.
And the thing is,
you can't fake who you are
or what you're about across huge
periods of time like that. There
are creators online that I know that
are viral
short-form content.
When you meet them in real life,
they're actually dickheads.
They're actually a bit dismissive,
and they think they're better than people.
They're the type of people
that kind of are rude to waiters
and waitresses.
But when you watch long-form content,
when you listen to people for hours,
you get
to understand what they're like.
That's why I brought back the podcast
because I
feel like getting hours
and hours in front of people,
it's a low-hanging fruit to
get people to like you.
And I've said before,
look at Chris Williamson.
All he does is ask people questions for a
living.
People go, "Oh,
you're business partners with Chris
Williamson from Nutonic." I go,
"Yeah." They go, "I love that guy." I go,
"What do you mean you love that guy?
All he does is ask questions."
And you're like, "Yeah,
he's fucking great." All he
does is ask questions.
He's not out here doing what I'm doing.
Value.
Helping businesses.
I'm helping put food on the table.
He's just asking Bugsy Malone questions.
Come on.
So the direction for 2026
that I'm going to be taking my cohort of
mentees is to
get that seven hours.
And I believe YouTube
is the easiest place to do that
because the average video on YouTube
is about 11 minutes.
It used to be 13, but it's now 11.
And the average video on Instagram,
I don't even
think it's a minute.
I think it's maybe 15 seconds.
So when we look at the amount of pieces of
content that we'd have to put out to
accrue that seven hours,
YouTube would be easier.
Now, Ed Lawrence did a video about this,
and I said I disagree with him, and I'm
going to explain that part in a second.
But the easiest place to get hours in
front of people is YouTube.
When I started social media back in 2014,
I didn't really get any
progress on YouTube till 2022. And
when I'm asked about it, people say,
"James,
why weren't you on YouTube sooner?"
And the answer is,
and it sounds weird to say
it, I wasn't man enough for it yet.
And when I say that, I'm not talking about
masculinity.
I'm talking about I wasn't well-rounded or
smart enough to operate YouTube.
I didn't know about audio.
I didn't know about editing that well.
I didn't know about what cameras I needed.
Because YouTube is a very,
very difficult platform,
and it took me years of
short-form content to get there. Now,
if you were to ask me, "James, where
is the
best platform for me to get clients
that will pay lots of money?"
I'd say YouTube. But if you were to say,
"Okay, I'm going to get my phone out now.
I'm going to start creating content.
Where should I be posting content?"
And I'd say Instagram.
And you'd say, "James,
you're a contradicting piece of shit." I'd
go, "Yeah." Let
me explain it. The majority of you
are going to be probably one foot still in
another business.
Maybe you're a physio rubbing people down.
Maybe you're a golf instructor spending
time at the driving range.
Maybe you're an accountant that's in the
firm. Cool.
I would say realistic YouTube videos,
one to two a week.
Realistic Instagram videos,
five to seven a week.
So some people out there say, "Oh, James,
it takes me two hours to put out a reel."
And I'm saying, "Right, okay.
That's your problem because you're putting
too much
effort and attention into a video." For so
many of you out there, volume is going
to be everything. There is
that famous story about two groups of
people both told to make a china pot.
One group is said, "Right,
you just need to make one china pot
and make it
perfect." The other group are told,
"You need to make as many china pots as
you can." And it's the group
that we're told to make as many as they
can, which had
the better china pot. Because they
were doing it so often and so frequently,
they
perfected the skill better than the people
that obsessed over making the one
perfect pot. So even in the onset,
even just picking up your camera
and recording
just like this, if you do 100 of those,
some of them are going to do better than
others. And you can look at that and go,
"Why did those do better than others?"
Then you can double down
and make better-performing posts on those.
But this is the point I want to make
clear.
So if we imagine that this
is a calendar month.
If you do YouTube across December,
that's all the amount of feedback
that you're
going to get from putting out your YouTube
videos.
And that just isn't a great amount of
feedback to have
when you're trying to figure
out what your audience want,
what they like, what you're good at doing,
how you're
good at presenting,
what problems to tap into.
Because so many of us,
for almost the first year of putting out
social media
content, we have no idea.
We're just figuring it out as we go along.
That's why I say to people
when they're like, "Oh,
I'm going to build a course."
I'm like,
"Just build a lead magnet first." They go,
"Why?" I go, "Because if you
create the lead magnet first,
you can determine the amount of interest
for it." For
instance,
if I wanted to start a company
that wanted to sell vests.
Before I go and order 1,000 vests,
I'd probably put it on sale before I have
the
stock and just see how many people try
and buy it.
Then if I get 50 people go to the checkout
and get to the cart before they're told
that it's sold out, I go, "Okay,
let's put in the order." But
if no one goes there,
I know I've made a mistake. So now
if we look at Instagram instead,
although the
impact and the amount
that people would watch
and the average view duration would
be massively smaller,
that frequency would allow you to pick up,
was your hook shit? Was your setup poor?
Was the ideation bad?
Did you lose attention? Because
if you can't hold someone for an Instagram
Reel,
you're not going to hold someone for a
YouTube video.
If your hook does not hold someone as
they're swiping,
your introduction on YouTube
is not going to get the person to remain
interested.
But there are other skills that you need.
You need confidence. You need pacing.
You need cadence.
You need all of these things
that you only learn through
repetition.
And here's another thing as well.
Short-form videos very rarely make you
rich. Very rarely.
You get a million views, you're like,
"Yes!" And this is actually the most
painful
point. Loads of people
that I work with in my mentorship I have
to get them set up
for their first viral video.
So we have to make sure they have a
landing page, they
have an email marketing sequence, so
that when that content does explode, they
capture loads of data.
Because although viral videos don't make
you rich, capturing
loads of data can make you rich in a few
months' time.
And often they'll say to me,
"I didn't enjoy making the landing page,
I didn't
enjoy all of the processes that we made,
but James, thank you so much for forcing
me to do this.
Just had a video get five million views.
I got 3,000 email addresses." Sweet.
But something happens to someone
when they've had a viral video.
I can see it in their eyes.
Because so much of what we do on social
media, we're
like, "Hopefully, this will work.
Hopefully, this will work.
Hopefully, this will work. Hopefully,
this will work." Then boom,
one video kicks
off and people go, "This does work.
My Instagram isn't shadow banned.
I'm not being held back." Because some
people, honestly, I get one a week,
someone
going,
"I'm thinking of deleting my Instagram
and starting again, because I don't
think this is working."
And they make up excuses like, "Hmm,
maybe it's because I
had my family and friends following.
Hmm,
because this account hasn't been posted on
in two years." And largely, that's
all bollocks. So
when you get someone to commit for
probably one to two years on a
short form, when that one video kicks off,
they generate aura.
And suddenly that person,
the next video they go to,
they just present better.
They're more confident.
They do things with camera angles.
They get more creative.
They have more fun.
They use a quirkier setup.
Because let's just say,
whether you go to Instagram or YouTube,
you're going to eat
so much shit.
You're going to eat more shit than you can
fucking ever imagine.
Welcome to the layer cake, son.
And this is just a part of content
creation.
Sure, we can work, we can ideate,
we can help you eat less shit,
but it's going to
be an inevitable part of things. Now,
quickly I'll just show you the sequence in
which you're probably going to need to get
clients. And imagine this.
Short-form content
is going to be the hardest.
There's going to be more people to compete
with. You're going to eat the most shit.
You're going to put out videos that bomb.
But in a couple of years' time,
you're going to be so well-versed at
short-form
content that when you go to YouTube,
you'll be a different beast.
When I turned up to long-form in 2023,
I was a different person, because I'd
spent so many years eating shit online
that it made me almost a YouTuber.
Okay, we're going to call this short form,
five to seven posts a week.
Objective, to get goodwill.
The idea of short-form content
is so people just go,
"Oh, never thought of that before. Oh,
that's interesting.
Hmm, I might try that." And
if you get that for someone five,
six times, they're
going to go, "Of course,
this person's a legend." They're going to
follow you.
Don't ask for a follow,
it's fucking pathetic.
Don't use hashtags,
they don't do anything.
Another thing you want to do in short-form
content is create something I've called
dinner table geniuses.
Educate people about something
that they once thought was
wrong or right,
like Coke Zero not being harmful for you.
Dinner table geniuses. And
if you do this well,
you'll get two outcomes,
growth,
and call to actions will actually work.
If you do not post enough,
do not generate enough goodwill,
and do not create
enough dinner table geniuses,
you may get the growth,
but you won't get people to
action your call to actions. Now,
the call to actions,
you can use something called
ManyChat. ManyChat means that
when people comment,
you can send them a message with
a link. So for instance,
we said Black Friday for Neotonic.
I'd say comment the word focus,
and then send them a DM with a link.
Now,
some people think about auto-following new
people. Don't do it.
Looks desperate, looks pathetic.
Instead,
have call to actions on your posts,
and then when people interact to get
your lead magnet or get whatever it
is that you're promoting.
Let's say you're a mortgage advisor
and you're giving out an asset that helps
people understand mortgages
and interest rates.
When you send them that, say, "Hey,
click here to download the asset. P.S.
If you need anything,
just ask me back." That's how you engage
in conversations in
DMs. Now, if they have loads
and loads of questions,
everything should be answered
by the landing page you send them to.
If they're like,
"I really want to jump on a sales call,"
just say, "Look, I'm
really busy at the moment.
Instead of doing a sales call,
just free your money-back
guarantee." And that's how you get clients
from that.
But the main thing I would rather you did
was spend your time on social media,
short form, get in their email address,
so you can nurture them away. Make sense?
Any questions, put them below.
I'll get them from. Long form,
slightly different.
Now, let's say one to two per week,
and let's just understand something.
If you do two videos per week,
the quality of the video
is probably going to be
half. But again, it's
that balance of frequency.
How experienced are you?
If you're not that experienced,
one a week, seven days to eat shit,
that's a lot
of effort to put in. Now, the next thing.
This is more important than your video.
People do not search on YouTube.
They're not searching for ways to lose
weight.
They're not searching for the best calorie
deficit. They are browsing.
They are turning their TV on.
They've sat down with their missus in the
evening.
They're scrolling through their browse
feed.
Your objective with your packaging
is to stop them in their tracks.
If you go how to create a calorie deficit,
everyone's like, "Fuck off, mate." But
if you were like, "Eating
and burning 10,000 calories in a day,"
they're going to
be like, "Oh, that's interesting. Is
that even possible?
Let's give it a little go." Then they
click on it, and then it's like, "Right,
I've
got 24 hours.
I'm going to eat 10,000 calories
and I'm going to burn it.
Is it possible? I'm doubting it."
And people are like, "Oh,
what an interesting
story." If you want people to actually
click on your packaging on your videos,
you will have to make it interesting.
Often a story, often a challenge.
Those things are what lure people in.
Now,
can't give you any better advice than
this.
If you have not got a good title
and thumbnail, don't do it.
If you haven't got a good title
and thumbnail,
make it a fucking Instagram Reel.
Now,
one of the beautiful benefits of this
is once you've created a
nice YouTube video, a lot of the time,
you can just make it a
Reel after. But I would reshoot it.
Don't just try and clip this up
and get Reels out of it.
Instead, if you've got all the props
and the research
that you've done for that,
just get your videographer and say,
"Let's make a Reel." The ultimate
objective of
this is to get people to go to the
description and to have links.
Probably one buy, lead magnet,
maybe even an offer.
Or like you'll have seen today, quiz.
And I know the mentorship lot watching
this,
you're going to be very excited to see
how I've done that. Again, I have put
that quiz together with a score app from
Daniel Priestley.
After he came on my podcast, we
were chatting about it a bit and
he's kind of got me quiz build.
I'm going to report back on all of the
quiz
data that I get to let you know what kind
of return on investment I'm getting from
it. So do that quiz,
because that'd be very interesting. Okay.
These Reels will not last very long.
Maybe like 24 hours in the algorithm.
But the good news is for these,
post it on Instagram,
it'll get pushed to Facebook.
You could go whack it on TikTok.
You could stick it on LinkedIn.
And you could even put it on YouTube
Shorts.
Don't know why I did the two there,
but anyway.
Long form, unfortunately,
it's probably only going to live on
YouTube. But you can put it on LinkedIn,
up to 15 mins.
Go on Facebook.
If you've got a long-form video
and you put it on YouTube, trust
me, just put it on Facebook.
You never know.
Even sometimes there's a consideration to
make.
So for instance,
this exhaust on my car was very expensive.
So that exhaust ended up costing more than
what I used to earn in a year, because
it's made out of titanium. Flex.
Sounds great though.
I said to Raz from Prestige Auto Works,
I go, "Bro, let's be real.
If you're going to make a YouTube video
about an exhaust, there's a certain amount
of views before you end up getting a
client." And I reckon, Raz, if you get
500 people to watch your video to the end,
four of them are going to be booking in
to get an exhaust done. So
when you're looking at YouTube,
ask yourself this.
Out of every 1,000 views,
how many clients am I going to get?
If it's five or it's 10
or whatever different price point, cool.
Just per 1,000 views, there
is going to be a certain amount of leads
or clients
you're going to get. So although this
is more short formed,
this stuff definitely
lasts for longer.
I've got one video at the moment
that flat-lined for four months,
and then it's just gone off like that,
and it's one of my biggest revenue
generators in RevTrack.
It's just the nature of YouTube.
Literally four months.
There's only one type of transition
that I am happy with people doing in the
world,
and it's not gender,
it's short form to long form.
Not to get political,
I just don't even understand any of
that stuff.
When some men out there go,
"I've just spent my whole life feeling
like a woman,"
I'm like, "Yeah,
but how do you know what
that is?" Because if you've never been a
woman,
how do you know what it feels like to be
one?
That's just a gap in the logic for me.
Do you know what I mean?
Anyway, I'll stay out of that.
Let's finish up.
Short form content bought my house,
built my life.
Sold out Hammersmith Apollo did so much
for me. I'm eternally grateful for it.
However,
long-form content for me has been the next
level up.
So my advice to you is this.
If you're new to content,
I want you to marry yourself
up with short-form content because I need
you to try different things, different
setups, different payoffs,
different hooks,
and I need you to just post and
disregard it.
If you watch Adam Sullivan's stuff
recently, he's literally just
pressing plus on his iPhone,
on his Instagram, just talking to it
and just posting
stuff.
There is going to be a spectrum where you
have high-quality content that
gets great returns
and low-quality content that doesn't.
I want a varied approach of both because
it's only through doing a mixed bag of all
of those things that you can find a
perfect middle ground.
This video today, for instance,
sits in that middle ground because it's
probably
about 19 minutes long. Actually,
it might even be closer to 22.
I scripted this video in 45 seconds before
recording.
I've got jujitsu in 13 minutes,
so I know that this video
is not going to get
150,000 views.
But I know it's probably going to get me
1,000 people to do the quiz
in the description,
probably going to get me one
or two sales from it because this
would've been the boiling point,
someone going, "Okay, I'm in." And it
was an
opportunity for me to tell you
that I'm probably going to take the next
four weeks
offline so I can build out the YouTube
course that I'm going to add to the
mentorship. YouTube
is the most difficult place to learn your
trade, but when
you get it, the returns are crazy.
But you cannot do it without first
finding out who you are, how you present,
how you talk, what you're interested in,
and better yet,
what your audience care about than
short-form content.
It is a journey from one to the other.
It is going from white belt to black belt.
And the best thing is, the more you learn,
the less videos you get to make.
I used to put a video out every single
day. Now it's what? Two a week.
Better for my mental health.
Then you on a weekly
and monthly basis can just feed
into producing people those seven hours.
And if you did a combination of podcasts,
live streams, YouTube, and short-form
content,
people would get through those seven hours
very, very quickly.
So please do check out the links in the
description.
Get excited for the YouTube course that's
coming.
And to help you with the binge effect
and also to help me with my average view
duration,
if you're not ready to click any of the
links because you're relatively
new to the content I'm putting out, well,
you can click this here.
This is called an end card,
and the reason I utilize this
is to get you into a
binge effect,
which increases my average view duration,
which tells YouTube, "Cor,
whatever this guy's talking about
is bloody useful." Thanks for watching.